In November 2024, a PlayStation
user noticed something… odd.
Logged in, Astro Bot on the PS
Store was $44.99. But when they
logged out, it was $59.99?
They shared it on Reddit.
Weird, but maybe just some kind of discount?
A year later, another post.
Red Dead 2, same region, even the same
PlayStation, but two different prices?
More of these began to pop up.
What was happening?
Then, the site PSprices, which tracks PlayStation
Store prices, reported that Sony had been secretly
experimenting with dynamic pricing.
Two users can secretly be given
different discounts.
Is this even legal?
Unfortunately, this is just the beginning.
Sony is trying to squeeze customers for as
much as possible, and something
far bigger is forcing their hand.
But it's not just Sony.
A gigantic battle over the
very nature of discounts is just beginning.
And some are doing much worse than Sony.
So, what was actually going on?
The team at PSPrices, the platform that tracks the
PlayStation Store, noticed something strange.
Tension
The store's public-facing API
started including weird strings.
First was "IPT_OPR_TESTING". It was
attached to 17 games in 42 regions.
Then another: "IPT_PILOT". 139 games
across 68 regions, but in particular,
a lot of Sony's own titles.
Then another in March: "IPT_LTM".
US only, 104 games.
What were these?
Users were secretly being assigned to control
and test groups. You might see a standard price,
or an experimental price, depending on the group.
So, the user who had a different price from his
wife? One would have been a control group and
the other a test group. Despite both being in the
same region and currency — even the same house.
"During the February PlayStation Store sales we
found that experiment participants received
a different discount percentage than regular
users. For example, HELLDIVERS 2 was sold
to regular users at -25%, while experiment
participants saw -56%."
But it gets even weirder.
IPT_LTM, for example — the US
one — was testing discounts
against each other, with much bigger discounts.
The retail price for GTA5 was $39.99. Some users
saw a discount to $29.99, others $26.99.
So what was going on?
People are calling it "Dynamic Pricing".
And it's "sort of, but not quite."
It's hard to say, but it doesn't seem like it
fluctuates enough based on real-time demand
to be called "Dynamic Pricing."
To be clear: no one was being
charged above retail. Some users were
getting bigger discounts than others.
What's actually happening is that
Sony is testing price elasticity.
This is something businesses do to figure
out how sensitive you are to price changes.
For Sony, using A/B testing, they're trying
to figure out how much they need to lower
prices to get you to buy. Who will pay full
price, and who needs a bit more of a nudge.
This sort of pricing already exists.
Airlines do this all the time,
which is why people frequently pay
different amounts for the same ticket.
Amazon and other big retailers
also do this, egregiously so.
And will send targeted coupons
to people based on their
shopping behavior or a "welcome back" discount.
Though very recently, this is getting a lot worse.
But for Sony, this feels different,
and unwarranted for video games.
There's a "social contract" with a
storefront. Everything is uniform.
Everyone sees the same discount. That was
the promise, unlike with airlines or Amazon.
Hiding the discounts feels a bit weird,
plus Sony's strong monopoly position
over the store basically means you pay
what they decide, or nothing at all.
And most of all: price elasticity
is also tied to supply.
Digital games don't run out. There's no supply.
No limited number of plane seats to fill.
Plus, what determines what group you're in?
Is it random, or something more
"tailored," based on behavior?
Gamers are, naturally, pretty annoyed at this.
More and more posts began popping up.
Another user had Assassin's Creed Unity
displaying a discounted price of £3.74
when browsed logged out, jumping to
£9.99 once they logged into their account.
But moderators deleted that one, annoyingly.
The media quickly picked up on it.
Push Square reported that "We've been
able to replicate this on the browser-based PS
Store; when logged in, we see the higher price,
and it swaps to the lower one when
we're not, just as shown above."
"This is absolutely ridiculous
and extremely scummy."
"Shame on Sony. I'll be buying even
less digital games than I already do."
Someone shared the PSprices article on
Reddit, which got 1,100 comments in four days.
But why is this happening now?
As it turns out, Sony is caught
right in the middle of a huge
change, and they're being squeezed.
If you work in marketing, SEO,
or have a website, you know
that a lot of decisions feel like guesswork.
Which topics to cover, which keywords to target,
where to spend your time. Lots of decisions to
make, but often with incomplete information.
So start making the right calls
with the full picture, with Ahrefs.
Ahrefs is a practical, everyday marketing
toolkit anyone can start using immediately.
It gives you free tools to understand your market,
find opportunities, and make
better marketing decisions.
Instead of wondering why your
site isn't getting traffic,
or what content you should be creating next,
Ahrefs gives you concrete answers, and for free.
Start with Site Audit. It runs a
complete SEO audit of your website,
flags SEO and technical problems, and shows
you exactly how to fix them. And no matter
your website, every SEO category is covered.
Then use Web Analytics to see how visitors
are actually behaving on your site. Where
they're coming from, and where you're losing
them. But Ahrefs is super fast, and lets you see
website visitors within a minute of their event.
Ahrefs also lets you create content
more optimized for visibility with
their AI Content helper. Spend less time
researching, and more time creating.
Ahrefs is designed to be deep for
experts, and easy to learn for beginners.
You can jump right in and start
improving your website, for free.
44% of the Fortune 500 use it to
make informed marketing decisions.
Whether you're a seasoned marketer or just
starting out, Ahrefs gives you the tools you need.
Click the URL in the description and head to
ahrefs.com/free and start using the tools today.
Thank you to Ahrefs for sponsoring this video.
To understand what's really going on… we need to
look no further than our old friend: big tech.
AI companies — NVIDIA, Google, Microsoft
— are paying premium prices for high-speed
memory at a scale that consumer electronics
manufacturers simply can't compete with.
But they're not really
buying the same RAM as Sony;
they're trying to get HBM: High Bandwidth Memory.
So, what does this have to do with PlayStation?
Well, consoles use a particular type of
DRAM: GDDR, and because companies are
making more HBM to keep up, they aren't
prioritizing other kinds of RAM. Micron,
the third-largest RAM supplier, has
left the consumer market entirely.
There's not enough to go around,
so prices have gone up a lot.
"DRAM contract prices have been revised upward,
from a previous estimate of 55–60% to now 90–95%."
So, Sony has a bit of a
problem: getting enough RAM.
In November 2025, Sony CFO Lin Tao told
investors that Sony had secured just
enough memory supply to keep PS5 hardware
profitable, but only through March 2026.
Anything after that wasn't
guaranteed. And it gets worse.
PlayStation hardware margins are pretty thin.
Under 10%. Way more than before, but still low.
[Piers Harding-Rolls, Ampere Analysis]: "It
is likely that Sony had price protections
for its components for a set period and this
may well have come to an end. With no sign
of prices easing ... Sony will have made the
move to protect its slim hardware margins."
To be clear: Sony as a whole isn't struggling.
Operating profits jumped 22% year-on-year in
Q3 FY2025. PlayStation alone brought
in around $900 million, up 19%. But
things were getting worse, and fast.
With this road of uncertainty ahead,
it gives context to some decisions.
In Sony's Q3 earnings call, February
2026 — right at the end of Sony's RAM supply
— CFO Lin Tao said something interesting.
"We intend to minimize the impact of the increased
memory cost on this segment going forward by
prioritizing monetization of the install base to
date and striving to further expand our software
and network service revenue."
The installed base — aka:
the people who already own a PS5.
So, what does all this have to
do with Sony's pricing experiment?
Sony takes a 30% cut from every PS
Store purchase, like Apple and Steam,
even if it's not their own games.
Something which they're currently being sued for.
But now they're trying to get their "install
base" to buy more, by testing elasticity.
Console margins are slim and getting slimmer,
so why not extract more from the
area with far better margins?
Users are now expecting a price hike to PS Plus,
with some threatening to cancel if they do.
Others are suggesting buying a year's
subscription now before the price jumps.
Though… dunno how that sticks it to Sony?
On March 27th, 2026. PlayStation Blog.
Isabelle Tomatis, VP of Global Marketing.
"With continued pressures in the global
economic landscape, we've made the decision
to increase the prices of PS5, PS5 Pro, and
PlayStation Portal remote player globally."
PS5 Disc Edition: $549.99 → $649.99. Up $100.
PS5 Digital Edition: $499.99 → $599.99. Up $100.
PS5 Pro: $749.99 → $899.99. Up $150.
Since launch in November 2020,
the PS5 Disc Edition has gone from
$499.99 to $649.99 — $150 more than
day one. (Lower third: With a
$50 increase in August 2025).
The PS5 Pro launched at $699.99 in late 2024.
It's now $899.99. $200 more in under two years.
I didn't realise the PlayStation was an
appreciating asset! I thought consoles
were supposed to get cheaper, guys.
People are now expecting the Switch
2 to also see a price hike.
And that's not even mentioning
the new digital license controversy.
(Highlight: "now require an internet connection
once every 30 days to validate the license")
The more things change,
the more they stay the same.
But something is changing.
This type of tailored, opaque pricing
from Sony is becoming more common.
There's a huge battle waging right now over
the very nature of sales and discounts.
More and more companies are trying to
change the way discounts work altogether.
Even worse than Sony, many companies will
secretly charge you more. And not at random.
Though I'm not talking about
dynamic pricing or surge pricing.
Where prices change based on general demand, time
of day, scarcity — why hotels cost more on the
same day as a big sporting event. That's normal.
I'm talking about surveillance pricing.
Instacart began using AI price experiments,
and a non-profit found that prices
differed by up to 23% per item.
Target's app will display higher
prices on the same products — like
$148 more for the same vacuum cleaner.
Even weirder, these price changes came
when you were inside the store, versus
on the far side of the parking lot.
Staples will charge you more if you have fewer
options — like if you're near a competitor.
Delta announced it would start
deploying surveillance pricing,
though it quickly backpedalled after backlash.
Hotel prices in Manhattan jumped by as much as
$511 per night when browsing from a Bay Area
IP address compared to Phoenix or Kansas City.
Don't even get me started on Amazon.
Though this pricing has started a war.
This year, lawmakers across the US
have introduced more than 70 bills
targeting surveillance pricing — travel,
grocery, rental markets, and now gaming.
On March 5th, 2026, the House
Oversight Committee formally
launched an investigation into it — sending
letters to major platform companies demanding
documentation on their pricing algorithms.
[Chairman Comer]: "Surveillance pricing can be
difficult to detect because consumers rarely
have a view into what information a company
has about them, what the prices they see are
based on, or what prices other customers may
be seeing for the same goods or services.
Often this takes place in a 'black box'
environment where consumers do not know
that personalized pricing is taking place
or what information collected
about them is driving prices."
Maryland just passed the Protection From
Predatory Pricing Act — the first law of its
kind in the US — banning retailers and delivery
services from using personal data to tailor
prices. Though it might not be enough.
Consumer Reports said it had "too many
industry-friendly loopholes, and
weak enforcement provisions."
But Maryland is just the beginning.
Hawaii, California, Illinois,
Kentucky, Connecticut — more than
a dozen states have bills pending.
Sony's pricing might not be as bad as some
of these other cases, based on your income,
location, or other private factors.
But it's along the same train of thought,
and experiments are often the
first step of a bigger plan.
The worst part of all these pricing
strategies is the lack of transparency.
In 1970, economist George Akerlof published
the paper "Market for Lemons," which won
him a Nobel Prize and changed the
way we understood the free market.
In the used car market, sellers know whether their
car is good or a "lemon," but buyers can't tell.
So buyers just pay the "average price," instead
of more for the good car and less for the bad.
With more information, customers
make better purchasing decisions,
and better quality products win.
But in a "black box," customers lose
and spend more for worse products.
Currently, Sony is in hot water
over another problem as well.
They make so much money from the PS Store because
they charge 30%, since they hold all the power.
But now they're caught in a multi-billion
dollar lawsuit, as some think this is an illegal
monopoly that has caused prices to be too high.
Click this video to learn the rest of the story.